Guide to the Division of Social Work, Marion Hathway Files, University of Pittsburgh, 1930-1938 UA.90.18.1
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Mothers Assistance Fund, November 1933-December 1937 (Box 5, Folder 157)
  Directory of trustees and executives of Commonwealth of Pennsylvania Mothers' Assistance, Pension or the Blind and Old Age Assistance Funds by county; Handbook for Administration of Old Age Assistance; What appears to be a student paper entitled "The Organization of the Job of Case Worker in the Mothers' Assistance Fund."; Application forms for various types of public assistance; List of "Persons employed temporarily for Old Age Assistance investigations …"; "Report to the Committee on Case Loads."; "Old Age Recipients Living in Institutions for the Aged in Allegheny County, Pennsylvania"; Student field work schedules.
- J. Prentice Murphy Memorial Fund, June1936-January 1937 (Box 5, Folder 158)
  Correspondence concerning Dr. Hathway's participation in an effort to raise funds I memory of J. Prentice Murphy for the benefit of his childrens' education; A letter containing a two-paragraph quotation from the New york Times paying tribute to Mr. Murphy.
- Murray, Clyde, May 1937-June 1938 (Box 5, Folder 159)
  Blank Weekly Field Work Report Form; Correspondence with Mr. R. Clyde Murray who was apparently associated with the Munhall Neighborhood House and who taught a course in the Division of Social work entitled Principles of Group Work.
- N - General Correspondence, January 1933-May 1938 (Box 5, Folder 160)
  Correspondence concerning the typing of Marin Hathway's doctoral dissertation; Correspondence with the chair of the Membership Committee of the American Association of Social Workers; Correspondence concerning Dr. Hathway's interest in joining an organization called "New America."
- National Conference of Social Work, October 1934-May 1936 (Box 5, Folder 161)
  Programs for National Conference of Social Work conferences; Correspondence including a letter promoting Sophonisba Breckinridge for president of the National Conference of Social Work in 1935.
- New School of Social Work, February-June 1938 (Box 5, Folder 162)
  Letter dated February 5, 1938 from W. I. Newstetter (at Western Reserve University) to John Weber, Secretary of the University of Pittsburgh, indicating that Pitt had been accepted as a full member of the American Association of Schools of Social Work. Newstetter was the AASSW's president at the time; A March 18, 1938 letter from Marion Hathway to Edith Abbott telling her that Hathway is resigning her Univeristy of Pittsburgh faculty position to become secretary (Executive Secretary) of the AASSW; Other correspondence among Hathway, Newstetter and Weber, much of it concerning the recruitment of a replacement of Hathway in her role as director of the Division of Social Work and the creation of a social work entity separate from Sociology; One item on the New School of Social Work in New York.
- Newstetter, Wilbur I., May 1936-August 1938 (Box 5, Folder 163)
  Correspondence with Newstetter regarding his authorship of a report on Group Work; personnel matters; preparations for a visit of Newstetter to the University of Pittsburgh; and the transition of the Division of Social Work in Sociology to independent School status within the University.
- O - General Correspondence, February 1934-August 1937 (Box 5, Folder 164)
  Correspondence regarding admission to the School, Poor Relief in the State of Washington; lectures on medical social work at Montefiore Hospital; other miscellaneous correspondence.
- P - General Correspondence (Box 5, Folder 165)
  Minor correspondence regarding the Division of Social Work's application for membership in the American Association of Schools of Social Work; Letters of reference; A list of social work courses offered during 1934-1035 at the University of Pennsylvania, University of Denver, Atlanta University, Fordham University, Smith College, the University of Chicago, Loyola University and others; A copy of the March 1936 membership list of the People's Lobby; Program of the Regional Conference of Progressive Education Association, May 1936; Correspondence regarding student recruitment, admissions and fellowships; Correspondence regarding the arrangement of speakers; The people's Congress for Democracy and Peace, November 1937; A report entitled "Old Age Recipients Living in Institutions for the Aged in Allegheny County, Pennsylvania"; Correspondence on various subjects with Dr. Kenneth L. M. Pry, Dean of the School of Social Work at the University of Pennsylvania; April 1938 acceptance by Dr. Hathway of an invitation to serve as a member of the Special Advisory Committee on Training and Personnel of the United States Children's Bureau; Other miscellaneous correspondence.
- Public Charities Association of Pennsylvania
  Dr. Marion Hathway's file from August, 1933 to March, 1938 concerning the Public Charities Association of Pennsylvania. The Association had its headquarters in Philadelphia. Its Executive Director was George R. Bedinger with whom Dr. Hathway had extensive correspondence on a variety of public and confidential subjects.
  - Correspondence (Box 5, Folder 166)
    August 1933 "Tentative Report of the Sub-Committee Appointed to Recommend the Program for the New Division of Family Welfare and Relief"; Extensive work on the Public Welfare Act of 1935 in Pennsylvania; Opposition to political patronage in the Pennsylvania Welfare Department under Governor Earle and promotion of a civil service or merit system; Minutes of meetings of the "PCA Committee on State Welfare Department"; List of the March, 1935 full and part-time faculty in the Division of Social work.
  - County Welfare Boards Plan, 1933-35 (Box 5, Folder 167-167a)
    Extensive correspondence, minutes, reports and correspondence in connection with the writing, passage and implementation of Pennsylvania's Public Welfare legislation.
  - Adoption Study Committee, September 1932-April 1935 (Box 5, Folder 168)
    Minutes from several area "sections" of the Public Charities Association of Pennsylvania Committee on Adoptions; Includes information on the "Ten Year Program Committee on Adoptions" and "A Plan for the Study of Adoptions in Pennsylvania.
  - Family & Child Welfare Committee, Advisory Committee, November 1932-January 1938 (Box 5, Folder 169)
  - Family & Child Welfare Division, Executive Committee, April 1935-March 1938 (Box 5, Folder 170-171)
    Minutes and meeting related materials from this committee of the Public Charities Association of Pennsylvania. Mrs. Mary Denman of Pittsburgh is mentioned. Mary T. Denman was a social welfare activist who earned her law degree from the University of Pittsburgh, taught in the School of Social Work, served in the Pennsylvania House of Representatives, was president of the Pennsylvania Conference on Social Welfare and a member of many ground breaking boards. She was known as a consumer advocate.
  - Committee on Penal Affairs, May 1934-May 1938 (Box 5, Folder 172)
    Legislative Program of the Committee on Penal Affairs of the Public Charities Association of Pennsylvania for 1934; Correspondence, meeting announcements, agenda, minutes and reports.
  - Mental Hygiene Committee, January, 1937 to May, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 173)
  - Committee on Public Assistance and Relief, May-December 1936 (Box 5, Folder 174)
- Pennsylvania Conference of Social Welfare, February 1934-April 1938 (Box 5, Folder 175-176)
  Correspondence, agenda, reports, conference programs, minutes, etc. from a very active organization in which Dr. Hathway was deeply involved; Arthur Dunham, Leon Stern, and other well known figures were also active; One of the reports shows 426 persons in Allegheny County were PCSW members while there were 215 members from Philadelphia; Materials and program pertaining to the Thirtieth Annual Meeting of the Conference on Social Work.
- Pennsylvania Social Work, July 1934- August 1937 (Box 5, Folder 177)
  Extensive correspondence between Dr. Hathway and a variety of persons regarding a new journal (Pennsylvania Social Work) first published in July, 1934. Dr. Hathway was the Chair of the Editorial Committee which appears functionally to have been the editor; One key article was pulled from the first issue at the last minute because of the objections of Miss Sarah H. M. O'Hare, Deputy Attorney General of Pennsylvania. The article concerned Veil Maternity Home, implicated in an active court case. Correspondence on this matter is included.
- Physical Examinations (Box 5, Folder 178)
  Policy statement on physical examinations of students to ensure that they are capable of entering the field. It contains the following statement: "Arrangements have been made to provide physical examinations for all students admitted to regular standing in the Division of Social Work. These are available without cost, through the University Health Service."; Lists of students eligible for the physical examinations; Reports from the University Health Service to Dr. Hathway giving the nominal outcome of these examinations by student's name.
  No restrictions, the outcomes in files 178 are vague.
- Placement Correspondence, March 1932-June 1938 (Box 5, Folder 179)
  Extensive correspondence concerning available field placements for social work students, some with remuneration, even room and board. Agencies as far away as Erie are mentioned; Some lists include names of agency directors; "Social Settlements" are specifically mentioned; Correspondence regarding employment opportunities.
- Prospective Students, March 1937-August 1938 (Box 6, Folder 180)
  Extensive correspondence concerning admissions.
- Public Affairs Committee, Federation of Social Agencies of Pittsburgh and Allegheny County, 1934-1938 (Box 6, Folder 181-182)
  Agenda, meeting announcements, annual reports and other materials from the work of the committee; A letter to the First Vice President of the YWCA of Pittsburgh commending the organization on allowing its facilities to be used "as a place of meeting for groups of young people intent upon discussing economic and social problems of the day" Attached are clippings reporting a "rally" held at the YWCA of the American Youth Congress, a group that apparently had communist leanings. One headline contains the words "Students Hear Red Doctrines Preached at Rally in Y.W.C.A."; A list of the 129 members of the Public Affairs committee including such well know figures as Mary J. R. Condon, Edgar J. Kaufmann, and Wilbur I. Newstetter. Dr. Hathway was the committee's chair; Confidential correspondence with the Federal Emergency Relief Administration
  Small file consisting largely of meeting announcements. A topic of major consideration was the campaign for merit (civil service) appointments of public employees in the human service sector
- Public Affairs Committee, Federation of Social Agencies of Pittsburgh and Allegheny County, Materials, 1935-1936 (Box 6, Folder 183)
  Reports, positions on proposed legislation, positions papers, etc. related to emergency relief, aid for the blind, labor, mental health, immigration and other social legislation; Lists of persons dismissed and their replacements on state social agency boards and in the state Department of Welfare. e.g. (1) Laura Porter was dismissed from the Bureau of Community Work in the Division of Assistance. She was the Assistant Superintendent of the State Mother's Assistance Office, had a graduate degree in social work from the New York School, 11 years experience with the American Red Cross and in hospitals. She was replaced by Ruth Zimmerman who had an undergraduate degree from a state normal school and who had volunteered as a secretary. (2) Florence Hall was a Wellesley graduate and had a graduate degree in social work from the University of Pennsylvania. She had 14 years experience with the Children's Aid Society and Children's Hospital. She was replaced by Ruth O'Boyle who was 22 years old, had completed nurses training but had no work experience. (3) Helen Glenn Tyson, Chief of the Bureau of Community Work and former Deputy Secretary of the Department of Welfare. Tyson was a Vassar College graduate and had a Ph.D. from the University of Pittsburgh. She had been Head of the University of Pennsylvania Social Service Department, organizer and first head of the State Mother's Assistance Fund, and Supervisor of Schools at Sleighton Farms. She was replaced by a Mrs. McCullough who had no professional training or experience whatsoever; Materials from the Special Session of the Pennsylvania Legislature for May, 1936; Course syllabus from the Second Semester 1935-1936 focused on the work of the Special Session of the Pennsylvania Legislature in 1936 and taught by Dr. Hathway: "Relief and Welfare in the Special Session"
- Q - General Correspondence (Box 6, Folder 184)
- R - General Correspondence, 1933-1938 (Box 6, Folder 185)
  Letter from F. A. Retka, Superintendent of The Orphan Asylum of the Holy Family/Holy Family Institute regarding student visits to the facility. Collaboration with this agency goes back to at least December 1933; Names of persons attending regional conference on Welfare Legislation; Correspondence with Bertha Reynolds regarding the potential employment by the University of Pittsburgh of Ruth Camblon; Correspondence with students, schools, public relief agencies around the country, publishers and others; Correspondence regarding invitations to speak; Other miscellaneous correspondence.
- Reading Lists, 1933-1937 (Box 6, Folder 186)
  Reading lists for various courses including a 1933-1934 Child Welfare course; Faculty represented include Marion Hathway, Arthur B. Thomas, Ruth B. Camblon, Clyde Murray, John Chornyak, LeRoy M.A. Maeder, and Verne Wright; Courses represented include Child Welfare, Seminar in Social Case Work, Principles of Group Work, History of Social Work, State and Social Welfare, Social Organization and others.
- Sample Reference Letter (Box 6, Folder 187)
- Regional Conference, 1938 (Box 6, Folder 188)
  Letter from Mildred Fairchild, March 16.
- Rehabilitation Advisory Committee, October 1934-November 1935 (Box 6, Folder 189)
- Registration, 1937-1938 (Box 6, Folder 190)
  Course listings for the University and other registration materials.
- Russell Sage Foundation, October 1933- April 1938 (Box 6, Folder 191)
  Correspondence between Dr. Hathway and the editors at the Russell Sage Foundation. The Foundation was also a publisher of the Social Work Year Book and the famous, 6 volume Pittsburgh Survey; In one letter, the editor asks Dr. Hathway to prepare an article for the next edition of the Social Work Year Book on the subject "Education for Social Work."
- S - General Correspondence, 1933-1938 (Box 6, Folder 192-193)
  Students, classes and registration of students; Social agencies on various subjects; Publication of Dr. Hathway's doctoral dissertation; League of Women Voters; Sccreditation (referred to as membership); List of "State Emergency Relief Administrations" by state for 1934; List of Pennsylvania Emergency Relief Administrations; Original questionnaire forms from 1935 for the "Social Study of Pittsburgh"; Letters of reference; Pennsylvania officials regarding policies and personnel of the Department of Public Welfare.
  Students and local and out of state social agencies regarding enrollment, scholarships, and programs; Speaking engagements; "The Social Workers' Club," including a brief history from 1909; Dr. Hathway's involvement with labor union activities; Brashear Association and the Hazelwood Community Council; Efforts by schools of social work to refute public statements by Emma Guffey Miller attacking social work education, especially in Philadelphia. Miller was a well-known public figure, an ardent suffragist and promoter of an Equal Rights Amendment to the US Constitution, a supporter of the New Deal and a member of the Pennsylvania State Welfare Commission. Therefore, her otherwise liberal public positions made her a formidable critic. Dr. Hathway and others sought to neutralize her attacks.
- Social Study Material, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 194)
  In 1934 and 1935, a study was conducted in Pittsburgh by Gordon Hamilton of the New York School of Social Work. The study appears to have been directed by Philip Klein. Professor Hamilton's report is 32 single spaced pages in length. In her introduction, Professor Hamilton describes the study in this way: "The following report on professional training in Pittsburgh and Allegheny County has been oriented chiefly to the relation between the program of professional education as now provided by Margaret Morrison Carnegie College, Carnegie Institute of Technology and the University of Pittsburgh and the needs of the social agencies in Pittsburgh and Allegheny College (sic) for trained personnel"; "Social Study of Pittsburgh and Allegheny County: The Group Work Field" Release No. 7 – Financing of Agencies in the Group Work Field, June 1936; Discussion Summary of Comment by the Faculty of the University of Pittsburgh Graduate Division of Social Work on "A Study of Training for Social Work"; A strongly worded, lengthy letter from the Executive Secretary of the Children's Aid Society of Allegheny County taking exception to the report by Professor Hamilton
- State Conference, Devember 1935-September 1937 (Box 6, Folder 195)
  The Pennsylvania Conference of Charities and Correction, which later became the Conference on Social Welfare" and still later the Conference on Social Work. Dr. Hathway was active in this organization that originated in 1909.
- State emergency Relief Training, June 1934-January 1936 (Box 6, Folder 196)
  Case studies used in training; Minutes and correspondence; Names and personal information regarding what appears to be trainers; State Emergency Relief Board forms and applications for clients.
- Student Lectures, March 1934-January 1935 (Box 6, Folder 197)
  Schedules and confirmations for outside lecturers to make presentations to students in the Division of Social Work; Lecturers included Dr. Philip Klein, Judge Gustav L. Schramm, Miss Isabel P. Kennedy, Mr. Maurice Moss, George Mills, Dr. Hovde, Wilbur Newstetter and others.
- Students' Organization in Social Work, May 1936-November 1938 (Box 6, Folder 198)
  Minutes, newspaper clippings, memoranda and correspondence from and about the Studen's Organization in the Division of Social Work; A substantial report of a study done by the Students' Organization entitled "Report on the Findings of the Committee on Field Work Facilities in the Public and Private Agencies of Pittsburgh."
- Summer Session, Division of Social Work, 1935-1937 (Box 6, Folder 199)
  List of late afternoon and evening courses for the 2nd Semester 1934-1935; List of courses in Social Work and Sociology for the Summer of 1935; Correspondence.
- T - General Correspondence, 1932-1938 (Box 6, Folder 200)
  Government reports, pamphlets and brochures; Student enrollment; Faculty matters at other universities; Local social agency issues and relationships; The possibility of Charlotte Towle teaching at the University of Pittsburgh; Faculty recruitment; Various research studies.
- Teagarden, Florence M.T., March 1934- August 1937 (Box 6, Folder 201)
  Correspondence largely with Dr. Florence Teagarden in the Psychology Department at the University of Pittsburgh concerning enrollment in psychology courses by social work students.
- Sidney Teller, Director, Irene Kaufmann Settlement, November 1933-March 1938 (Box 6, Folder 202)
  Copy of report entitled "Housing Statistics for the City of Pittsburgh Released by the Bureau of Business Research of the University of Pittsburgh"; Correspondence regarding student placements at the Irene Kaufmann Settlement; Correspondence regarding the League of Social Justice and the Pittsburgh Civil Liberties Committee; Correspondence regarding the donation of materials on housing by Mr. Teller to the University; Other miscellaneous correspondence.
- Thesis Projects, 1934 (Box 6, Folder 203)
  The file contains one 5-page memorandum entitled "Research and Thesis Projects in the Division of Social Work in the University of Pittsburgh." It consists largely of a list of thesis topics in family dependency, child welfare, courts, medical social work, public relief, historical studies, community organization, professional standards, public welfare, and special groups and problems.
- Towle, Charlotte, October 1935-March 1937 (Box 6, Folder 204)
  Correspondence devoted to the planning of an "Institute on Supervision" given by Charlotte Towle in Pittsburgh in April, 1936; Some correspondence on a second visit to Pittsburgh in March, 1937.
- Travelers Aid and Transient Service, National Association of, April 1937- September 1938 (Box 6, Folder 205)
  Correspondence largely with staff and executives at the national level in the National Association for Travelers Aid and Transient Service; Correspondence concerns visits and guest speaking arrangements for both Dr. Hathway and Travelers Aid personnel.
- Travelers Aid Society, November 1937-December 1938 (Box 6, Folder 206)
  Newsletters; Travelers Aid cases; Case procedures; Correspondence regarding collaboration between Travelers Aid and the School of Social Work
  Travelers Aid Societies were federated under the National Association of Travelers Aid and Transient Services.
- U - General Correspondence, 1933-1938 (Box 6, Folder 207)
  Social Work Curriculum at the University of Buffalo, 1933-1934; Correspondence and invoices with publishers; Other miscellaneous correspondence.
- Urban League, December 1937-May 1938 (Box 6, Folder 208)
  Correspondence with the Urban League regarding student field work, thesis work, an appointment to the League staff, a visiting speaker and other miscellaneous matters.
- V - General Correspondence (Box 6, Folder 209)
- W - General Correspondence (Box 6, Folder 210)
- Women's Association (Box 6, Folder 211)
- Worker's Schools in Western Pennsylvania (Box 6, Folder 212)
- X,Y,Z - General Correspondence (Box 6, Folder 213)
- Young Men's Christian Association (Box 6, Folder 214)
- Young Women's Christian Association (Box 6, Folder 215)
- YMCA and YWCA (Box 6, Folder 216)